Module 4, Interfaces for Abstraction,
Topic 1.1, Polymorphism.
Polymorphism is a property
very commonly associated with
object oriented programming.
It's the ability for an object to have
different forms depending on the context.
Okay, so what does that mean,
different forms?
That could mean a lot of things, but
what it typically means is you can have
a function or method with one name, area.
And it does one thing for
one object and another thing for
another type of object, okay?
So for instance take area, okay?
If you want to compute the area of
a rectangle, that's base times height.
You're going to compute the area of
a triangle as one-half base times height.
A function name is going to do two
different things depending on the context.
If you're doing it with
respect to a rectangle or
with respect to a triangle, so
that's what polymorphism is.
So you would say area is
polymorphic because it
can do two different things
depending on the context.
So another way to think about it is
that these two area implementations,
they are at a high level of abstraction.
They're identical.
What they do is they compute the area,
right?
No matter what the object is,
if it's a rectangle or
if it's a triangle,
the area is what's computed.
So at a high level, forgetting the detail,
they do the same thing.
At the low level and
how they actually compute the area and
they are different, right?
So really polymorphism is a way
of establishing an extraction.
These things are the same at
the high level of extraction.
But underneath they're different, right?
So that's what we want to allow.
It's useful for a lot of reasons.
So we need Golang to have some
type of support for polymorphism.
So what I'll first describe is how
polymorphism is usually implemented in
traditional object oriented languages.
So one thing that is usually used
in object oriented languages
to support polymophism is inheritance,
and Golang does not have inheritance, and
so I'll just say that again,
Golang does not have inheritance.
Inheritance is where you get a series
of classes, and they have this class,
subclass, superclass relationship,
or sometimes you call it parent and
child class, parent class, child class.
So the superclass is the top level class,
and
the subclass extends from the superclass.
And the subclass inherits the methods and
data of the superclass.
So as an example,
maybe I've got a speaker superclass, and
a speaker is supposed to represent
everything that can speak, all right?
Anything that can make noises,
okay, you call that that a speaker.
Now, underneath speaker,
a subclass of that might be cat and
it might be dog right?
because cats can speak.
They can make noise.
Dogs can make noise.
So maybe I've got this subclass cat,
subclass dog.
Both subclasses of this
superclass speaker.
And cat and dog will both inherit
the properties of the superclass.
So my superclass speaker,
let's say it has a method called speak.
And that just prints out whatever
noise the creature makes.
So speaker, since it's generic, and
the superclass, its speak method will
just print out noise,
arbitrary noise because it's generic.
But then the subclasses cat, dog,
they'll also have a speak method.
They'll inherit it from
the speaker superclass.
So they get the same properties,
they extend down.
So cat and
dog are different forms of speaker.
And this is where the polymorphism,
they're different forms of each other,
this is where polymorphism
concepts come into play.
And remember that Go
doesn't have inheritance.
Now, inheritance is one thing that you use
in a regular object oriented language
to support polymorphism, but you also,
on top of that, you're going to
need another property, overriding.
The ability to override a method.
So a method is overridden,
a subclass overrides a method when it
redefines a method that it
inherits from the superclass.
So in the example we're talking about
here, you've got the superclass speaker.
And under that you've got
the subclass cat and subclass dog.
And speaker has this speak method and
cat and dog inherit the speak method too.
But without overriding the speak method,
the cat speak method and the dog speak
method do exactly what the superclass,
what the speaker's speak method does.
They just print out noise, right?
Which is arbitrary.
So what you want is for the cat
speak method to print out meow, and
the dog speaker method to print out woof.
So what happens is,
that's called overriding.
The cat subclass will redefine the speak
method to print out what it wants,
meow, right?
And then the dog subclass will redefine
it to print out what it wants, woof.
So now the speaker class, the speaker
superclass, it has its speak method, and
cat also the speak method,
dog also the speak method.
But the cat speak and the dog speak
do two different things, okay?
So cat and dog classes have overridden
the definition of the speak method with
their own new definition
of the speak method.
So now you can say speak is polymorphic.
Because speak, it has two different
implementations for each class.
So speak in the context of the cat,
it'll print meow.
Context of the dog, it'll print woof.
But the idea is to support
polymorphism which you
normally see in object oriented language,
you see inheritance, and
then you also see the ability
to override a method.
So both the subclasses
inherit the speak method, but
then they can override it and
define it the way they want.
And one thing to note is that
they actually use the same,
even though they're overriding the method,
they use the same signature.
So this function signature is,
the method signature is the same.
So this method speak,
it has the same name, in both cat and
dog class, it has the same arguments and
the same return types.
So the signature will stay the same and
you'd call it polymorphic in that case.
Thank you.