Module 4: Interfaces for Abstraction,
Topic 1.3: Interface
versus Concrete Types.
So concrete types and interface
types are fundamentally different.
A concrete type is a regular type,
it specifies the exact representation
of the data and the methods,
data specifically, but also methods that
are used in the type of the receiver type.
So, they're fully specified, and it has
complete implementations of the method,
of all the methods.
So any methods that use this
type as a receiver type,
they're completely specified.
But the first thing is sort of a big
difference between interface types and
concrete types is that the exact
representation of the data is in there.
So if you have a concrete type,
it's going to have a bunch of data, one or
more pieces of data that
are associated with the type.
And interface type just specifies
some method signatures.
So no data is specified, just the methods.
And even the methods,
the implementations are abstracted.
You don't have implementations, you
just have the signatures of the methods.
So that's the difference between the two.
But remember that when
you give an interface,
interface eventually gets mapped to a
concrete type, we'll see that in a second.
So an interface value, when you create an
interface you declare an interface type,
you make a value of that type.
You can treat it like other values,
ints, floats and all this,
you can make a variable of that type.
So I can make a variable of
the type of a particular interface,
like my shape 2D,
I can make a variable of that type.
Now an interface value, the value of
an interface like that has two components.
First, there's dynamic type,
second there's dynamic value.
So dynamic type,
is a concrete type that is assigned to.
So the dynamic value though is actually
the value of that dynamic type.
So the dynamic type is just
the type which it's associated to.
So to be more specific,
let's say we're talking about shape 2D,
that's my interface, right.
This interface, there are several concrete
types which satisfy my interface, like
rectangle, that satisfies my interface,
triangle satisfies my interface.
Now when I make my interface variable and
I give it a value,
that value has gotta be
mapped to a concrete type.
Maybe it's mapped to a rectangle, or
a triangle, or something like that.
And that rectangle, triangle, whatever
it is, it's going to have a value.
So the rectangle might have
some points in it, and
the triangle might have some points in it.
So there's a dynamic type which is
the type of the concrete type that
the interface value is assigned to.
And the dynamic value is
the value of that dynamic type.
So an interface value is actually a pair,
the dynamic type together
with the dynamic value.
This probably will become more clear
within the next lesson given a bit of
an example.
So defining an interface type, so
we got this type speaker
interface speaker interface.
And all we define in there
is the speak method.
Which takes the arguments and returns
no values, so very simple interface.
So that's our interface type at the top.
Now then I also defined my dog type, okay.
And it's a type called dog, its structure,
and it's got just a string in there, okay.
The name of the dog let's say,
name, it's called name.
So it just got, that's my whole dog type.
And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to make this dog type,
make it satisfy my speaker interface.
So I declare a function called Speak,
it's receiver type is Dog.
And it just prints the name of the dog,
d.name, so that's what the dog speaks.
So now, Dog is a type that
satisfies the Speaker interface.
In my main the first thing I
do is I declare a speaker.
So an s1, s1 is a variable and
is going to actually have a speaker value.
So it's a speaker type,
it's going to be a speaker value, right.
So s1 is an interface value.
Next I declare a dog, [LAUGH] a d1,
it's going to be my dog type.
It's going to have a name equal to Brian.
Now then I can say s1 equals d1.
Now, that is legal because the dog
type satisfies the s1 interface.
So S1 can be a dog because it
satisfies the interface, so
I can say s1 is equal to d1.
So now s1, s1 is a speaker type,
its concrete type that
is assigned to is d1.
That is the concrete object that it's
assigned to, which is the concrete type is
going to be the dynamic type
is going to be the dog type.
And the value is going to be the dog
value, which he's name is Brian.
And then I can say s1.speak, and
it'll call the speak of the dog,
which we'll just print out Brian.
So the Dynamic type in this case
of s1 is Dog, is a Dog type.
And the Dynamic value is d1 which
contains that name Brian, okay.
So this s1 which is a speaker object,
it is, sorry,
it's a speaker object which is
an interface, it is a pair.
The Dynamic type Dog, that's the type,
and Dynamic value, Dynamic value,
which is d1 in this case.
Which has this Dog name, name Brian,
that's all it has in it.
Okay, so an interface, just to repeat,
has dynamic type and dynamic value.
Now interface can have a Nil Dynamic
Value, meaning no dynamic value.
It can have a type, a dynamic type but
not a dynamic value.
So let me give you an example of that.
[COUGH] We got a variable,
s1 is the speaker, okay.
Then I have my dog d1 and I make it
point to a dog, *Dog, then I say s1=d1.
Now when I do that,
I'm assigning s1 to d1, but d1,
it's not a concrete object it's type is
Dog, or *Dog, it's pointing to a Dog.
But it doesn't have any data in it, okay.
So remember Dog has this data,
this name, which is a string.
But d1 is a pointer to a Dog,
so it's not an actual Dog,
it doesn't have the data in it.
Okay, so
d1 has no concrete value at this point.
But it have a type, okay, it's associated
with a dog, it's appointed to a dog.
So what that means is when I do
that assignment s1 equals d1.
S1 has a dynamic type,
dog, or dog pointer, but
has no dynamic value because d1 doesn't
have a dynamic value yet, right.
because d1 is a pointer to a dog,
it doesn't actually have dog information
in it, namely the name, okay.
So this is a situation where you got
an interface that has a nil dynamic value.
Nil means nothing,
it's sort of the empty end goal.
So it has a nil dynamic value but
it has a dynamic type.
And this is legal, to have a dynamic
type but no dynamic value is legal.
So when you have that situation,
when you have an interface like that,
with a dynamic type but no dynamic value,
you can still call the methods of s1.
So in this case, s1,
its method is speak, right.
That's the method that's
defined in the interface.
And Dog, or
at least it's specified in the interface.
And then Dog defines that method, right.
So when I say Dog defines that method,
there's a method Dog who's receiver type
is Dog,
method speak who's receiver type is Dog.
And that method is fully specified.
Now this s1, it has a dynamic type.
The fact that it has a dynamic type
means that the compiler knows that when
you call Speak,
call that speak method on s1.
It could look at the type and say,
the type is dog, the dynamic type is dog.
So I know that the method implementation
that I want is dog method implementation.
So it can call that function, that method
speak even without having a dynamic value,
all it needs to know is the dynamic type.
The dynamic type is enough information to
go find which implementation Speak you
want to use.
Now, it would be wise inside
the speak function to check,
to see if the variable has
a dynamic value or not.
But the point though, is that you can make
the call even without a dynamic value,
all you need is a dynamic type.
So we take a look over here,
we got this function Dog,
Speak rather, and its receiver is Dog.
And notice inside the function it says
if d == nil then it prints ("")
some generic thing, else it prints
(d.name), it prints the dog's name.
Now what that does is it checks saying
d == nil It checks look,
does this have a dynamic value or not?
If it doesn't have a dynamic value and
d equals nil then it just
does what it says there.
Prints noise because it doesn't
have a dynamic value yet,
prints something generic.
L, so if it does have a value then it
knows it can actually access dname,
d.name, and so it prints out the name.
And then the rest of the code maybe
that would appear inside a main or
something like that,
which I'm not drawing here.
But so I declare this speaker as one,
I declare the Dog pointer d1.
I set s1 to d1 so now s1 has
a dynamic type but no dynamic value.
And then I can call s1.speak and
it works, right.
A class one does speak even without the
dynamic value because it can figure out,
the compiler can figure out,
I see s1 is mapped to d1 which is a dog.
So I can find the dog, the method is
bigger that is associated with dog that
I had to find up above, so
this is actually legal.
So the point of all this is
it legal to have a speaker,
sorry an interface, with a dynamic
type but not a dynamic value.
And in that situation,
you can still call the method of
that interface, so it is legal to do that.
Now we'll be wise like we do here
to check inside the method if
the dynamic value is nil or not, right.
Because you might want to do something,
for instance if we didn't do this check,
this is where we say if d equals nil.
If we didn't do that check, we might try
to print D.name, even though D was nil,
and that would throw an error at run time.
So we don't want to, it's probably
wise to check it but it's allowed.
This is a legal state, to have
a dynamic type but no dynamic value.
Now on the other hand,
people use a term nil interface value,
this describes an interface
with a nil dynamic type.
So not only does it not have a dynamic
value, it doesn't have a dynamic type, and
that's a different situation.
[COUGH] In that situation,
when you don't even have the dynamic type,
then you cannot call
the methods on that interface.
Because without the dynamic type,
you can't know which method
you are referring to.
So for instance,
here If at the top example I
got the speaker s1 dog d1 and
I say s1 equals d1.
So it has a dynamic type but
no dynamic value.
So the compiler configure out if I go to
call speak It would be able to figure out,
I see, it's the dog's speak.,
the one whose receiver type is dog.
But if I have a nil dynamic type, so
if I just say VAR S1 speaker and
leave it at that.
Then I don't have a dynamic type yet
because I haven't assigned s1 to anything,
right.
So s1 is just sitting there with
no dynamic type, no dynamic value.
And in that state there's
no actual method to call.
He tried to call a speak on that,
it would throw an error because
there's no method implementation.
Remember to interface
doesn't specify the method,
it doesn't give
the implementation of the method.
It specifies just the name and
the arguments and the return value, but
it doesn't actually define the method.
So if you just say var s1 Speaker, there's
no method that it is associated with.
There's no speak method associated
with s1, so this would throw an error.
So the point here is summarized that
if you have no dynamic type and
no dynamic value on interface,
then you can't call the methods
of the interface, thank you.