Module 4, Interfaces for Abstraction,
Topic 2.3, Error Handling.
So I just want to show a common
use of interfaces in Go.
The Error Interface.
So there are a lot of different Go
functions that are built into packages,
which return errors.
And when I say return errors,
what they do is they return whatever
they're supposed to return, and then
their second return value is an error.
An error interface.
So and we see it defined over here.
The error interface just is any type
that satisfies this interface, and
error interface just specifies that you
have to have a method called, error, which
prints the error message essentially which
prints something, some text that's useful.
So under correct operation,
the error return might be nil,
so for instance, let's say,
I want to open a file.
If it opens the file correctly,
it'll return nil for the error, and
there's no problem.
But if the error actually has a value,
then you'll probably print the error,
and it'll call its error method,
which will successfully print the error.
So show you an example of that.
So basically the idea is, when you,
this happens, there a lot of different Go
language function like this, which return
error as the second argument, okay?
And so, when that happens, you should
check that error, after the call, and
handle it if you need to.
So you can see on the top line,
we're opening a file.
So os.open, open the file by that name,
and it returns two things.
One is the file F, and the second
thing is an error, if an error exist.
So then, right after that, for
safety's sake, you should check the error.
So if error not equal to nil, so if it's
equal to nil, you're fine, you go on.
If it's not equal to nil,
then, do a print that sort of
the most obvious thing to do to handle
the error, is just to print it.
So you println(err) and return.
So printing the error, the format package,
the fmt package,
which println is a part of.
That package will call the error method
of the error to generate the string,
and print that string.
And so, this is sort of the generic
way of handling errors in Go.
It's a very common way
to handle errors in Go.
Thank you.