Welcome to the course, Course One.
The point of this course is to give you
some first-tier working knowledge of the Go language and how to use it.
I'm assuming that you already have some experience programming in other languages,
so I'm not talking from scratch here.
I'm assuming you already have seen a lot of these concepts.
You know data types, you know things like this,
but maybe you're familiar with C or Python or
Java or something like that and you want to move over to Go.
Maybe you want to start programming systems devices right.
You want to do some more low-level stuff
but you don't want to go straight to C, let's say,
or you've been dealing in C in a long time and you want
your life to be easier right? Something like that.
In fact, Go on the whole is a sort of sweet spot,
where it's efficient, close to C,
but it's also easy to use like say maybe Python or Java, has a lot of that.
So it's in-between, and so we're going to just hit on all the basics in this class,
in this particular course,
and you should be able to program something and get
a feel for it and see if you even like this language at all,
and if you can be comfortable with it.