Welcome to the second module.
We're going to start talking a little bit more detail about the Go language,
we'll talk about datatypes in Go,
the basic data types.
That's what this module is really about.
We'll go over data types you've seen in other languages, integers,
floats, booleans, strings, variations, all those.
So, you can change the length of the integer,
length of the flow, things like this.
So we'll talk about those data types,
we'll talk specifically about how to declare them,
how to create them and what functions are available for them.
So what functions can you apply to integers?
What functions can you apply to strings and booleans and flows?
Once you're done with this,
you'll be able to use basic data types inside your Go code.