So we've
already talked about strings.
Strings are a common construct.
You see them in every
programming language, and
strings are made of unicode Unicode runes.
They're straight,
basically, a raid of runes.
So, there's a package called the Unicode
Package which provides a set of functions
that actually evaluate the properties of
the different runes inside the strings.
And it's useful if you've
ever done parsing, you know,
you want to parse some
string out of whatever file.
Or out of a- maybe something somebody
typed in directly as user input and
you want to evaluate that string
when you're doing parsing you need
functions like these so
there a long set of functions that
the unicode package provides to
evaluate the runes Some of them here,
are IsDigit tells you if the rune
is a digit, a numerical digit.
IsSpace- is it a space character?
isLetter is the letter lowercase,
IsPunct- is punctuation so
these are all binary- boolean right so
they return true or false depending
on if the rune is what it's saying it to
be, if it's a digit or space or so on.
There aree also a set of other
functions that perform conversions.
So some of these conversions ae possible.
For isntance ToUpper and ToLower.
You can take a lower case (r rune),turn
it into an upper case (r rune).
And vice versa.
So they provide funtions for that.
So they take a (r rune), like ToUpper, it
takes a (r rune), Which is lowercase and
returns a which is uppercase and so on.
So a unicode package is useful for that.
But there are other packages that are also
involved in manipulating strings.
There's the strings package.
So the strings package.
The functions that it provides
are things to directly.
Not looking at the individual generally,
but look at the whole string.
So there are a set of search
functions it provided.
Inside the strings package.
These are common functions that you see
in lots of different lanugages also.
So for instance,
the first one would be compare.
Compare (a, b), you givev it two strings
and it compares to see if they're equal.
And actually this compare function,
it returns a -1.
It returns 0 if they're equal,
it returns a -1 if a is less than b,
meaning earlier than it,
in In alphanumeric order.
And A, it returns a positive one,
if A is greater than B, so
if A is later than B
in alphanumeric order.
So, to compare, contains, so you give
S a string, and then a sub string,
if that sub string is contained inside S,
it returns true, otherwise false.
Have prefix so
you give it a string s and a prefix.
If that and returns true, if that prefix
is the, s starts with a prefix and
index s and you go to substring,
what that does is a search,
it searches for the substring inside s.
And it returns you the index
of where the first instance,
instance of that substring can be found
inside a [INAUDIBLE] can be found.
So, this is the string's package.
Now, the string's package also provides a
set of functions that manipulate strings.
Now, when I say manipulate, you can say
changes string, a string is mutable.
But, there are a lot of functions
that take an existing string and
return a new string.
That is some modified and some useful way.
So the first one will be replace.
With replace you basically take a string
and it allows you to replace instances
whenever it finds it in a current of old
it replaces it with currents of new.
So these are all strings.
So there's a big string S Is a substring
old and another substring new.
Replaces instances of old
with instances of new.
And return to a new string.
So s the original string
is not actually changed.
It returns you to a new string
with a replacements for ToLower,
ToUpper, so this'll take the whole string
and change it to lower case or upper case.
I keep saying change.
It does not change the string.
It returns a new string that is modified.
Also, trim space is useful.
That gets rid of leading and
trailing light space from a string.
So you get this a lot when you're
reading from a file with, say, and maybe
the tokens in the file are seperatedby
spaces, so if you just read directly
in the file, you'll also read these
spaces in, but you don't need the spaces.
You just need the token.
So you may call TrimSpace
to get rid of the spaces.
Another package that has
a lot of useful functions for
strings is the Strconv Package.
So generally this provides a set of
functions for converting strings
from different basic data types, to and
from different basic data types.
So some of the big ones are Atoi As
ascii to integer is what it stands for.
And converts a string to an integer
if that string represents an integar.
Lets say,
you are reading a string from a file and
the string is a number 123 one hundred and
twenty three.
Now when you read that, and
you read that as a string,
You can't do math on a string, right?
You can't take that 123 and
add 1 to it because it's a string type,
it's not an Int type.
So you need to read that string in and
convert it to an Int.
And then you can do math on it.
So you'd use Atoi to do a thing like that.
And Itoa does the reverse.
It converts an Int into a string,
an equivalent string.
Then FormatFloat basically does
a similar thing for float.
So it converts a floating point number
into a string representation of that
floating point number.
And then ParseFloat does the opposite,
converts a string to
a floating point number.
So a string, so if you have a string.
123.45, and
in a string it can convert it into
a floating point the number
you can actually do method.