[MUSIC]
So, Control Flow describes the order
in which statements are executed inside
a program.
Now, basic control flow, the most basic
control flow is just executing one
statement at a time,
one after the other, right.
A procedural control flow, just top-down.
Now, the control flow changes for
a lot of reasons.
But the first reason why
control flow changes is because
the programmer inserts control
flow structures into their code,
which changes the sequence in
which the statements are executed.
So the main control flow structure,
the first one, is an if statement.
Basically, with an if statement,
you can conditionally execute
certain sequences of code.
So if this condition is true,
then you execute the sequence of code.
If not, then you don't.
And this, what we're showing here,
is the most straight forward if
statement without an else clause,
you can also have an else clause, but
I'll just start with the basic one first.
So the structure is just if, condition,
you write some condition in there,
x is greater than 5, or
something like that, and
this condition has to
evaluate to a boolean, right.
If that condition is true, then
whatever is inside the curly brackets,
label consequent there, that's executed.
And you can have any number of
statements inside there, and
that'll be executed if
the condition evaluates to true.
So this changes control flow because
instead of just definitely executing
the next statement one after the other,
it checks its conditions.
If the condition's false,
then that consequent,
those statements in the consequent
are not executed at all.
And so, we can see at the bottom,
we got, if x is greater than five.
And then it prints,
it performs a print state.
And if it's not,
then it just skips that entirely.
Now, this if statement,
this is a very vanilla if statement.
You could also have an else
clause after that, right?
So if the condition's true, it executes
what's inside the curly brackets.
Then, you could have a next clause,
the else clause.
It would execute whatever's inside
the next set of curly brackets,
the next block for the else, right?
We didn't include one here, but
this is a straightforward extension.
And you see this in every major language.
So for loops, they're another
form of control flow statement.
Again, so for loops, what they do,
basically, they're loops.
So the control flow,
rather than just going top-down,
when you hit the bottom of the loop,
you come back to the top of the loop, and
you do it again and again until
a certain condition is met or not met.
So that's how they alter control flow.
It's just, and these are extremely
common in programming, using loops.
So, they just iterate over a block of
code, as long as the condition is true.
Now, there's several forms of for
statements,
we're looking at one right here.
Probably the main and most common form.
You see it similarly in C and
things like this.
If you look at that keyword for,
right after that,
there are three statements, really.
There's the initialization statement,
init.
There's a condition,
and there's the update.
And separated by semicolons.
So the init is executed once
at the beginning of the loop.
So, the first time you hit the for loop,
it executes the init just to
initialize things, right at the top.
Then, the next block, that condition,
that is checked on each iteration.
So at the beginning of each iteration,
that condition is checked.
It has to result, it has to be
an expression, that results to a boolean.
If that condition is true,
then it executes all
the statements inside the loop.
Otherwise it doesn't,
otherwise it's done with the loop, and
it continues past the loop.
So that condition is
the termination condition.
It determines when you
stop executing this loop.
because as soon as that condition is not
true, you skip the loop and you're done.
Now, the update, that third block there,
the update is what is executed at
the end of each iteration, and
it's used to act as some
element of a state.
So a very common way in which
you use is you'll have,
you'll have some index variable for i.
i equals zero, maybe start off with i
equals zero, and you want to do this,
iterate through this ten times, so the
condition might say, i less than 10 and
then the update would be i++,
or i=i+1, right?
And then every time, every pass
through it updates that i value,
that element to the state.
And one thing about these for loops is,
unless you want an infinite for
loop which you typically do not want, you
gotta make sure that that condition is,
at some point, false, right?
because if the condition is always true,
then you never leave the loop.
So the most common way to make sure that
condition's always false is to make sure
that update changes
the state in such a way that
eventually the updates cause
the condition to be false.
So for instance, if I say i is equal to
zero, I start off being equal to zero,
and my update is i equals i+1,
then eventually i will be greater than 10,
so the update guarantees that
the condition is eventually false, and
that you eventually drop out of the loop.
So here are some forms of for loops, these
are three most common forms of for loops.
The top one is what we've already seen.
You've got the initialization,
you got the condition you got the update.
The next one,
if you look at the for keyword,
there's only the condition check after it.
No initialization, no update.
You don't have to have those.
Now, instead, what we did here to make
it equivalent to the for loop before, we
had to put the initialization before the
for loop, that's another way of doing it.
And the update is now built into the for
loop, so if you look,
there's an i plus plus inside the loop,
right.
So, it's actually inside the fourth block,
instead of, as you have in the first form,
where you actually put it in
there right after the keyword.
But, it's another way
you can define a for,
which is really just like a while
loop inside another language.
Then, the last form is
just an infinite loop.
It has nothing after the for loop,
it just is an infinite loop,
which is not typically what
we are going to be doing.
You do that, maybe,
in an embedded system but,
it's not common to do
in a regular program.
You usually don't want an infinite loop.
All right, so another type of
controlled flow is a switch.
Switch is paired with case, right?
So a switch is a multi-way if statement.
So, you often get situations where you
want to say, if this is true you do this.
If this is true, you do that.
You sort of, you do one of a set of cases.
Sort of an else if, if else if is
another way to write this type of thing.
So a switch is like,
there's a set of cases and
only one of them is going to be executed.
Whichever one matches.
So the switch may contain,
typically contains,
a tag, which is a variable to be checked.
Right, so maybe I say switch x.
So that's the variable I'm going to check.
Then each case is associated with some
constant value that x is compared to,
that the tag is compared to.
So tag is compared to the constant
defined right after the case keyword.
And then whichever case is constant,
matches the value of X, that's the case
that's executed, and none of the rest are.
So, in this example,
you can see, you got switch x.
Inside you've got two cases.
Case one, case two.
So if x is a 1, it will execute case one.
If x is a 2, it will execute case two.
And then the bottom one is default.
Default is executed if
none of the cases are hit.
So it's an optional thing.
You don't have to have a default.
But you can have it default so
if it falls through,
it'll end up executing something.
So this is a typical form for a case.
And one thing to note, just if you're
used to C, is in comparison to C,
the case automatically breaks
at the end of the case.
So in C, If you were to execute case1,
say x was equal to one, you hit case1,
you execute case1, it would also follow
through and execute case2, right?
That's what C would do,
unless you put a break statement in
there at the end of case1, right?
After the fmt.Printf,
you put a break statement,
then it would skip the other
case in the default.
In switch in Go lang,
you don't have to do that,
it automatically breaks,
which is a good, good thing.