Module 1, Functions and Organization.
Topic 2.1, Well-written Functions.
So we're going to talk a little bit
about how you should write functions.
Now, this isn't actually
necessarily specific to Go.
But this is more good way
to construct your code so
that your code is well-organized and
easy to understand, okay?
And understandability, I'm highlighting
this idea of understandability.
It is important to be able to
understand your own code for many,
many reasons, okay?
Mostly for debugging but also maintenance,
other people interacting with your code,
it needs to be understandable.
And the way you write your functions,
the way you define your functions
really impacts understandability.
So if we look at a block of code,
we could roughly
say that a block of code is a bunch
of functions and a bunch of data.
So a bunch of functions that are the
operations that you can perform and
the data that you're going to
perform the operations on, okay?
So you can see really any block of code,
any program as a pile of functions and
a pile of data somehow organized together.
So when I say understandability,
when I say, this program is
understandable, here's what I mean.
I mean that If you're asked to find
a feature, you can find it quickly.
So as an example,
where's the function that blurs the image?
Let's say your writing
some graphics program,
where is the function
that blurs the image?
You can locate that.
Now, you might be asking that yourself,
right?
Because you found a bug,
something is not working,
you need to find that piece of code.
Or that could be some kind
of code review meeting or
you're dealing with other
people you're working with.
And they need to understand
how your code works and
they ask you this type of question.
Maybe it's your boss, right?
Your boss is like, look,
where's the code that does this?
And you will look like an idiot
if you can't answer that.
It's your code, you wrote it,
you should know it, right?
So you need to understand
the organization of your own code.
Now, a lot of this is memorization, but
it's also a matter of organization.
If you organize it well,
it is much easier to find things.
So where's the function that does
this operation, blurring your image?
Or where do you compute the average score,
whatever the question is where
is the code that does this?
Where is the code that does that?
You need to be able to find that, okay?
And that's an understandable piece of code
if you could find that pretty easily and
even better if somebody else can find it.
So if you write the code and
you give it to somebody else because
you're probably working on a team, right?
And that other person can find
where the image is blurred or
where the average scores computed.
If they can find it quickly, that's
a real measure of understanablity, right?
And remember this too,
I know a lot of students in my classes,
they underrate how important this is,
right?
They think, look, it's my code, of course,
I know how to understand my code, right?
So believe me, if you write
a complicated piece of code and
you walk away from that code for a month.
You come back, you will lose track
of what the heck that code did,
you will not understand your own code,
okay?
So you really want to construct in such
a way that it is easy to figure out where
these features are located
inside your code.
Now, another aspect of understandability
is finding where data is used, because
often you'll get some kind of problem
where this data is incorrect, okay?
Or this data is not just used.
Actually, I said, where data is used,
also where data is used and
where it's defined, right?
So this data is incorrect,
how did it get incorrect?
What part of your code
actually affected that data?
That type of question you
want to be able to ask.
So you want to be able
to trace through data.
You'll say this data, where is it used?
Where is it defined?
So
where do you modify the record list,
right?
So you got some record list,
you realize that record list,
the contents of that list are wrong,
right, while you're debugging.
Where did you modify that?
You've gotta find that so
you can find where the bug is, right?
Where did you access the file?
Maybe the file has the wrong data and
you want to know what code
that's affecting, right?
So where did you access that file?
Where did you access these
different pieces of data?
So this is what I mean by
understandability, you need to be able to
find a feature, find the code dedicated
to a particular feature, find it quickly.
Also data that could be wrong, where is
that data used and where is it written to?
So where is it used and
where is it modified,
you need to be able to find it quickly.
And an organization, writing a code,
writing a function and
organize where it really
helps you with that.
So very basic debugging principles and
there are a million debugging principles
but I'm going to just be really basic now.
So say you run your code,
the code crashes.
And it crashes inside some
functions somewhere, right?
So some function you wrote, it crashes
on line 100, right, some function.
So I can broadly say that there are only
two ways that this could go wrong,
two options for any kind of bug, okay?
It could be that the function that
failed is written incorrectly, okay?
It just did the wrong thing, okay?
So maybe as an example,
it's supposed to sort a slice, and
it sorts it in the wrong order.
Okay, it did the wrong thing, right?
So the function could do the wrong thing
or maybe the function is written perfectly
well but the data that
the function uses is incorrect.
So maybe this function is,
it sorts the slice just fine but
the slice has wrong data in it, right?
So somehow the data that it got is wrong
so when it does a sort, of course,
this result is going to be wrong, right?
Because the original data was wrong.
So the function that you're working on,
it could be messed up or
its inputs could be messed up.
Now, its inputs, remember,
can come from the parameters, right?
So they could be, or even sit past to it.
But these inputs don't
have to come from there.
They could come from maybe a file or
some user input or something like that.
So you gotta think of all these inputs.
So this is just my sort of high
level debugging principle.
And notice how I'm dividing this,
I'm saying look,
either function is written incorrectly,
or it's the data is at fault.
So it's the function written wrong or
the data is at fault.
Now, of course, when you trace that back,
you'll see the data is probably incorrect
because some function
wrote it incorrectly.
But locally, you can say, look,
either this function is wrong or
the data that it's working on is wrong.
So, in order to support debugging,
when you run into a bug like this,
first thing you've gotta be able to do
is understand your own function, okay?
So functions need to be understandable.
So when you look at that function,
look at the code,
you gotta be able to look through it and
manually say look, is this right?
Is it doing what I think it's doing?
It's actual behavior, does it match
what I want, desired behavior?
So your function needs to be
written in understandable way so
you can determine that
without too much difficulty.
The next thing though is
the data needs to be traceable.
So what that means is, is maybe your
function is perfectly fine, but there's
some input data that it got past that
somehow it access that was wrong, okay?
So you need to be able to figure
out where that data come from,
so you can follow back to where the
original fault actually happens, right?
Now, this could be easy, it could be hard.
Global variables for one complicate this.
Because one thing about having no
global variables is that the inputs to
the function come straight
from the parameters.
So you know where every piece of data came
from, it came from the caller, right?
But if you use global variables,
then they can come from whoever
wrote to the global variable.
And since these variables are global,
anybody could have written to it.
So it's much harder to trace back
which function is at fault for
writing the wrong data to a variable.
That's exactly why global variables
you should be careful about.
And I'm not going to say never use them.
People use them, and there are reasons,
I use them sometimes, but
just understand that they
add this complication.
They make it hard to debug just because
you know this data is incorrect,
you don't know what
the source of that was.
And then you've gotta do something
more complicated to figure that out.
Thank you.