Module 1 : Functions and Organization.
Topic 2.3 : Function Guidelines.
So another thing that you want to do with
functions is you want them to be not too
complicated.
You want them to be understandable,
they shouldn't be too complex.
Now this term complexity, when you
measure the complexity of a function,
this is definitely arguable.
People have different opinions
on what comprises complexity,
what makes up the complexity
of a function.
So we'll start out off
with function length,
because that's sort of the most obvious.
Everybody uses that as a very rough
approximation of function complexity.
So functions need to be simple, and
one way to make them simple
is make them short, okay.
Now this doesn't always work, because
short functions can be complicated.
I have definitely seen that,
especially in a C or
something, you can put
everything into one line, right.
Yeah, I'm not counting lines that are,
you could technically write a whole
go program in one line, right?
Assuming you use regular line separations,
that's what I'm talking about when
I'm talking about function length.
And you could rely on number of lines,
line count.
In fact, I remember one professor here,
he basically insists for NC that all his
students write their code, every function,
is no longer than 10 lines.
I think that's too strict,
sometimes you gotta go over that.
But I see where he's going with the idea,
right?
It forces you to have some measure of
simplicity in each individual function.
So the question then is, so how do
you write a complicated piece of code
with these really simple functions, right?
I mean, some code you write
it has to be complicated.
And there's no real avoiding it, right?
So what you can do is,
when you define your functions,
you can make sure that each individual
function isn't too complex.
You can make attempts to limit
the complexity of an individual function.
And what's going to happen is,
in your code in general,
there's always what I'm calling
here a function call hierarchy.
Meaning you've got a function, and
it calls some other functions,
which call some other functions and so on.
I'll call that a hierarchy, right?
This calls that,
which calls that and so on.
So you can use that hierarchy to
simplify the complexity of
each individual function.
So, as an example, I've got Option 1.
Option 1 you write
everything in 1 function,
1 big fat function 100 lines long.
Or I can go to Option 2.
Now, Option 2, now I have 3 functions.
Instead of 1, I've divided it into 3.
The first function, in this case,
is really short, right,
with just a few lines,
but it calls the other 2.
And then, the other 2 functions
are each 50 lines long, right?
So this is an approximation
of what you'd do.
But in Option 1, you've got one big
complicated piece of code 100 lines long.
In Option 2, you've got 3 pieces of code,
2 of which are 50 lines long.
But the complexity of each individual
function, if you're measuring in terms of
lines of code,
is less in Option 2 than in Option 1.
So presumably,
Option 2 would be easier to debug.
Now, this all depends on
a bunch of other factors.
So for instance, you don't want to take
a piece of code that's 100 lines long and
just chop it straight in half.
And say, the top half's function 1,
bottom half's function 2, right?
You've gotta group the functions
in a reasonable way.
We already talked about this.
Each function should map to an operation
that makes sense in your application.
So you can't,
typically you can't just cut it in half.
But you might be able to take this 100
line piece of code and say, well, the fist
30 lines do this and the next 70 lines
do that and maybe chop it up like that.
And even that's an improvement, right?
And then you can take the 70 line piece
of code, that 70 line function, and
chop that up into a 30 line chunk and
a 40 line chunk and so on.
So there's this decomposition and
hierarchy that you're making implicitly
when you define these functions.
And the goal is, part of the goal is,
to make sure that each individual
function isn't too complex, okay?
So you limit the complexity.
Now, in this case, we're talking about
complexity in terms of lines of code.
But we'll talk about another
form of complexity next.
Control-flow complexity, so
another way to look at the complexity of
a piece of code is to look at how
complicated its control-flow is.
So when I say control-flow, I'm talking
about the paths from the top of
the function to the bottom, from the start
to the end, the control-flow paths.
So how many options there are?
So, for instance, if you had a piece
of code that had no if statements,
just straight line code.
Just a sequence of assignments, let's say,
assign, assign, assign, assign, assign.
That has exactly 1 control-flow
path from top to bottom.
There is 1 sequence of instructions
that you will execute in that code, so
1 control-flow path.
But if you put an if statement in there,
if this is true, you do one thing.
If that's true you do the other.
If you put 1 if then you've got 2 paths.
Now code gets more complicated than that.
You can have nested if statements,
you could have loops,
which are implicitly conditional
statements, and things like this.
So a typical function can have
many different control paths, many
different sequences of instructions that
are executed when you execute that code.
Many different sequences that execute
depending on the input parameters, right?
So here I got this function,
foo, and it's got 2 conditions.
Well, actually,
one is nested within the other.
So if a == 1 than you go into
this next conditional if b == 1.
So if I look at this code,
I would say this has 3 control-flow paths.
Assuming there's no other control-flow
operations here, you got 3 paths, 3 paths.
1 is where a == 0, a is not equal to 1.
If a is not equal to 1, then you skip
that whole inner conditional, if b == 1.
And you just finish and
go to the end, okay?
So that's one path, a is not equal to 1.
Then another path is a == 1,
but b is not equal to 1.
Then another path is a == 1 and b == 1.
And each one of those
3 sets of conditions,
you are executing a different sequence
of instructions inside this program.
So there are 3 control-flow paths
inside this piece of the code.
Now, one way to measure
the complexity of a piece of
code is how many
control-flow paths it have?
So I can say, look this has 3.
So, say I want to simplify that,
and I might be able to use
functional partitioning to reduce
the control-flow complexity a little bit.
So, say I take that function,
foo and now I take,
remember it had 2 conditionals, right?
So now what I've done is
I defined 2 functions.
And I've separated the conditionals, split
them out across the 2 different functions.
So now foo still has the first
conditional, if a == 1.
Still got that, but
then the next conditional check doesn't
exist anymore inside that function.
Instead it calls a function called CheckB.
Now if you look at CheckB on the other
side, that has the other conditional,
if b == 1, then whatever.
So I've separated these 2 conditionals,
now, now that I've done this,
the foo function now has 2 paths
through it, a == 1, and a is not.
And then CheckB, it has 2 paths,
b == 1 and b is not.
So now each 1 of these functions
has 2 control-flow paths instead of
the 3 control-flow paths that I had
when I merged them together, okay?
So this is just a tiny example, but
the idea is you could separate the
conditionals into different functions and
reduce the max complexity, right,
the max number of control-flow paths.
You can reduce that overall, making
the code easier to debug, typically.
Thank you.