Welcome to Module 3.
Now, we're talking about composite datatypes.
So composite data types are data types that aggregate other data types together,
so they bring together lots of different data types.
Specifically, we're going to be talking about arrays,
slices, maps and structs.
Composite data types are essential for complicated code,
for real code, because simple data types,
basic data types aren't enough to describe the conflict,
concepts that you're going to need to refer to in big pieces of code.
So you need to aggregate them.
Maybe you have strings here, integers there,
you merge them all into one thing that describes
whatever the concepts are that you're referring to in your particular application.
What you've done with this, you'll be able to use
more complicated composite datatypes inside your Go code.