Module 3, Object-Orientation in Go,
Topic 1.1, Classes and Encapsulation.
So, classes are part of
object-oriented programming paradigm.
And this class, this whole course is for
intermediate level people, right, so
I'm assuming that people already
have exposure to programming.
And so it is most likely that you
already understand what object oriented
programming is, although I will
sort of redefine it right now,
make sure we have a common understanding.
And there's always this question,
does Golang support object
oriented programming?
I'll say yes it does.
It doesn't have classes exactly,
but it has something equivalent,
it allows most of the same features.
So just to say what a class is though
to start, what a traditional class is,
that you would've seen
in many other languages.
A class is basically
a collection of data fields and
functions that share a well
defined responsibility.
So it's data fields and functions put
together, usually called methods.
You call them methods
when they're in a class.
So data and methods put together.
[COUGH] So as an example,
say we want a point class, right,
that represent some point in 2D space.
So, I'll use a geometry
program I'm making, okay?
So, the data might be the x coordinate and
the y coordinate of the point,
that's data that you would
associate with a point.
The functions, there might be a variety of
functions, but maybe I've got distance to
origin, quadrants, returns the quadrant
that the point's in, AddXO set, AddYO set,
set X, set Y, there are a lot of
functions that I could put in there.
But the point is though, that the data and
the functions are all related
to the same concept, okay?
There is a two-dimensional point and
these functions are all things that
you do to two-dimensional points.
And the data is all the data that's
associated with two-dimensional points.
So, that's what a class is.
Now remember,
a class is actually a template.
So the class contains data fields but
not data.
What that means is,
when you make this Point class,
I'm giving a template on how
a point should be created.
I'm saying, here's the data that a point
should have and here's the function that
should operate in that data, but
I am not actually providing the data.
So a Point class is really a template for
a point.
An actual point has to have data,
has to have an x coordinate and
a y coordinate associated with it.
So an object is an instantiation of
the class, an instance of a class.
So it contains actual data.
So, as an example, say in my geometry
program that I'm trying to make,
I have a triangle and
this triangle has three points on it,
three coordinates, (0,0), (6,0), (5,5).
So there are three point objects
that I want to create, and
I call these objects now.
These objects, they're made based
on the Point class template so
they have x coordinate and y coordinate
just like the template says, but
they have actual values for those.
So the (0,0) point will have 0 and
0 for the x and (5,5) point has 5 and
5 and so on.
So for one class you can have many,
many objects of that class
that instantiate that class.
They have actual data in them
that fill in the data fields.
So, just want to make clear the difference
between a class and an object.
Encapsulation is another
concept that's usually
associated with object
oriented programming.
Actually, you know what,
I would say it's associated with the use
of abstraction in general, but right now,
we're talking about it in the context
of object oriented programming.
And the idea behind
encapsulation is that you might
want to hide data from the programmer,
okay?
So when I say the programmer, I mean
the programmer who is using your class.
So, the person who's defining the class,
you can't hide anything from that person.
But if there's a programmer
who's using your class,
you might want to hide some data,
conceal something.
So you might want to make the data,
allow the data only to be accessed using
the methods that are part of the class.
So rather than allowing the programmer
to just go straight in and modify,
say it's a point, just go straight in and
modify the x and the y values as a point,
we might instead say, look,
if you want to modify it,
you have to use this method to modify it,
the method that's provided in the class.
And why would you do this?
Maybe we don't trust the programmer
to keep the data consistent,
that's the main thing.
Not that we don't trust the programmer,
but
the programmer has a lot of things on his
or mind, might make a mistake, right?
So we want to relieve the programmer
that burden of dealing with the internal
consistency of the data.
So we just say look, programmer,
if you use these methods to
modify the internal data then we,
the people who made the class, guarantee
that the data will stay consistent, okay?
So you, as a programmer, you don't have to
think about that, just use our methods.
So that's encapsulation.
Where you say look, the internal
data can't be accessed directly from
the outside, or at least part of it can't
be accessed directly from the outside.
You basically put up a wall,
a hard abstraction barrier,
which are the methods that
you use to access the data.
So as an example, let's say I've
got a point and a function, and
I want to do this point is to double
its distance from the origin, right?
So I want to double its x and double its
y so it's twice as far along the line
between the origin and the point,
you want to move that point,
you want to scale it, to double it,
right, double its distance.
So you gotta double the x and
double the y.
So option one is to make
a method to encapsulate, right?
So you make a method
called double distance and
it does exactly that function.
That's the safe way.
Another way is to say look,
I don't want to make that method,
I'll just let the programmer
directly access the x and y, and
the programmer can double the x and
y when they want to.
The problem with that is what if
the programmer makes a little mistake, and
doubles the X but
forgets to double the Y or
doubles the X and
triples the Y or whatever?
Whatever the mistake, if a mistake
like that happens then the X and
the Y values inside the object
are now inconsistent with each other.
And so a mistake was allowed to be made,
where if you force them to use this
Double Dist function that you made and
you know you debugged it correctly,
then they can't make such a mistake.
Thank you.