Module 3: Object-Orientation in Go,
Topic 1.3: Support for Classes.
Now, in a normal object directed language,
it's a class is defined, it's data
associated with some kind of methods.
And usually,
you can associate lots of different data,
you can roll up lots of
different variables.
Maybe an anti-float, whatever type
of data you can put a lot of it,
as much as you want together.
And then associate that
with any number of methods,
asnd you can do the same thing in go.
Of course, you're going to use a receiver
type, just like we talked about,
you don't have classes,
you have receiver types.
But you can just use a type
that has lots of data in it.
So, before we're using examples where
the type was just an int myant, right.
It was just an int, one piece of data.
But it's very common to use a struct as
a receiver type, a struct of some kind.
So structs basically allow you to compose
all kinds of different data fields.
So in this case, my point struct,
I'm just composing two numbers,
an x and a y, both floats.
So two floating point numbers,
they're composed into one struct.
But remember,
with a struct you can compose an arbitrary
amount of information,
you can put together.
So it's very common to see a receiver
type be a struct of some kind with
lots of different data.
It's a traditional feature of classes,
people just roll lots of
different data together.
Now, the structs with methods, you could
take a struct and define it as a type,
like we just did with that point type.
And then you can associate
methods with that type.
And then you get what you would normally
think of as a class in another language.
You get the struct with lots of different
data, associate it with as many different
methods as you want to
associate it with struct.
So, we got an example of that right here,
we're using the point that I
defined just in the last slide.
So, this point, I want to make
a function called DistToOrigin, and
I've defined it right there.
Notice that to the left of the name of the
function DistToOrigin, I pass it a point,
p Point, right?
When I say I pass it,
it's an implicit pass, right.
So it doesn't have any explicit arguments,
but its receiver type is a Point called p,
and that will be implicitly
passed to DistToOrig.
And then if you look at the function,
the insides of it, the internals,
it's just doing the Pythagorean theorem,
right.
It's squaring the x, squaring the y,
adding together,
then it returns the square root.
So it just does Pythagorean
theorem nothing sophisticated.
Then in my main, I can make
a point p1 is three comma four and
then I can just call p1.DistToOrigin.
And that p1 together with its x and
y coordinates will be implicitly
passed to dist to origin.
Dist to origin will then
do Pythagorean theorem and
return the distance which is
five in this case, thanks.