Module 4, Synchronized Communication,
Topic 1.1 Blocking on Channels.
So a common operation on a channel
is to iterate through the channel,
so iteratively read from the channel.
So this would happen in a scenario
where you had a producer and
consumer, the consumer is receiving
from a channel, and it just wants to
continually receive data from the channel
and then process it in some way.
Very common scenario, receive data
process, receive data process, and
you just continue as long
as the code is running.
So there's a concept made to do
specifically that, this for for range.
So we've already seen for loops, but
you can use this range keyword to
continually just read from a channel.
So, for instance,
here we say for i = range c.
What that'll do is, that for
loop will just continually
iterate one path for every piece of
data that is received on that channel.
So every time a piece of data
is received on that channel,
i is assigned to that data, and what's in
the curly brackets is executed, right,
the for loop is executed in one pass.
And, it'll just continue forever, or
not forever, until a close happens,
I'll talk about that in a second.
But it'll just continually read
data off of that channel and
assign it to this variable, i, or
whatever variable you want to call it.
Now in this case, and to our example, I'm
not doing anything useful with the data,
I'm just printing it, but you could
be doing anything in there, right?
You just process the data and
use it in some way.
So this is a very common thing to do.
Now, this for loop,
it could be an infinite loop, right?
So what has to happen is, in other to end
of this loop, when does it actually quit?
It quits when you close the channel.
So this is another method on a channel.
You can close a channel,
so you can see it,
I have it in the last line,
highlighted in red.
The sender, the person who's doing the
sending, it can call close on the channel.
And if they call close on the channel,
then the receiver realizes close,
and this for loop will end.
Now, you don't have to ever
call close on a channel.
It's not like a file,
you don't have to call close on a channel,
unless you're doing what I'm showing here.
Unless you're using a range construct.
If you use this range keyword
to forever read from a channel
you need to close the channel,
the sender needs to close the channel.
So that the receiver eventually
knows I can quit this loop
because now this channel is done.
So the only time you would call close on
a channel is if, as a sender, you knew
I am never going to send more data on this
channel again, then you can call close.
And that basically sends a message to
the receiver to say now this channel is
closed so you can jump out of the loop
whose range you're iterating through.
So this is sort of a very common
thing to read from channels.
Now, another thing that you might want to
do is read from multiple Goroutines, okay?
From multiple channels really, which can
be associated with multiple Goroutines.
There might be attributes associated
with the same Goroutine but
reading from multiple channels,
put it like that.
So, let's say in this example,
I got these three Goroutines, T1, T2, T3.
T3 is receiving data from T1 and T2.
And, from T1, it's receiving on Channel 1,
C1, and T2 is receiving on Channel, on C2.
So T3 has these two channels
that it's receiving data from.
Now, there are different scenarios
about reading from multiple channels.
Maybe, like in the case I'm showing here,
maybe you need data on both channels.
So for instance, totally it depends on the
application, but let's say T3 is trying
to compute the product of the two numbers
we're starting from T1 and T2, okay?
So if that's the case then
you do what I'm doing here,
just read the two channels sequentially.
A = arrow c1, b = arrow c2.
So you read from both channels, and
then once you get them both
then you print the product.
Fine, it does the product.
So in this case, T3 actually
needed data from both c1 and c2,
it needed both channels to complete
it's task, the product, right?
And these are blocking, right?
These are blocking, so the first read will
wait until something is written under c1,
but eventually, T2 will read from
both of them and it'll do its task.
But this is an example where you
need data from multiple channels.
But sometimes you have a choice.
So sometimes you got a Goroutine which
can read from different channels,
but it doesn't have to read from all
of them, it just needs one of them.
One or the other, so
sort of there's an or relationship.
You can get from this one, or this one, or
that one, you don't need all the channels.
So if you have a situation like that where
you have a choice of which data to use,
and whichever data comes in first
that's the one you want to use, right?
So, say you got two channels, c1 and
c2, data could come in on c1,
data could come in on c2.
In this scenario,
whichever one comes in first first come,
first serve that's the one I'm going
to use and do something with, okay?
In that situation, you don't want to read
from both channel 1 and channel 2, right?
If you read from both of them then
you're blocked on one of them.
So say data gets sent on c1,
that read will work.
But then the read on c2 will never
happen because maybe data never gets
sent on c2, right?
So you don't want to wait on c2 when
no data is going to come, right?
And vice versa.
Maybe data comes in on c2 but
not on c1, right?
So you don't want to have
to wait on both of them.
In the last slide, we waited on both
channels, c1 and c2, because we
needed data from both channels and we knew
the data would come in on both channels.
In this scenario, we just need
data from one of the channel and
we don't know that data is going
to come in on all channels.
Data might just come in on one of
the channels, and so we don't want to
wait on all of them, we want to wait on
one of them, but we don't know which one.
So that's the case we use a select
statement like I'm showing here.
So select statement allows you to wait for
the first data from a set of channels.
So in this case [COUGH] we
got two cases actually.
So in the select you got the first case,
the second case.
First case is waiting on c1 to write
it to a, second case is waiting on c2.
And whichever one of
those two happens first,
that's the one that's
going to get executed.
So if the data comes on c1 first
it will do the first case and
it'll skip the second case,
and visa versa.
Thank you.
Module 4, Synchronized Communication.
Topic 1.2, Select.
So we've been talking about select, and
I showed how select allows you to choose
data from one of several channels.
You don't have to block
on all the channels,
you can just block on
the first one that comes in.
The first one that satisfies when
data comes in, then you just wait for
that and you can continue
your execution more quickly.
Now, the way I described it before,
I was assuming that we were
blocking on receiving data.
But we can also block on sending data too.
So, with select, your case can either
be receiving data from a channel or
sending data on a channel.
So I have that here.
Let's say my first case I say a is
assigned to be arrow inchan, right?
So I have some input
channel called inchan.
And if something comes in on that,
they're eager to sign to that, and
you print received a.
Now the other case, instead of
a receiving it's a sending thing.
So in the other case I'm taking some
number, b, I don't know what that is.
I'm taking the number, b, and
I'm writing it to outchan.
Now, note that either one of
these two cases can block, right?
So reading from inchan, that will block if
nobody's actually sent anything on inchan.
And outchan, write into outchan will
block if nobody is receiving on outchan.
So either one of these
two cases can block.
And what happens with select is,
whether it's a read or is a write,
whichever one of the cases is unblocked
first, that's the case that's executed.
So, in this case, if some data
came in on inchan first before
outchan became available,
then you would execute the first case.
Otherwise if some other Goroutine
did a read on outchan then
the second case would be executed first.
So I'll select either send or receive.
You can block on either sends or
receives and select one of them,
whichever one completes first,
that's the one you execute.
Now, one common use of a select is
to have a separate Abort channel, okay?
So say there's some task that you're doing
over and over, you're reading data and
processing it, right?
So this is producer-consumer
scenario again, right?
Something is producing some data and
sending it on a channel to you,
the consumer.
And your consumer, his job is
basically to receive the data and
then do something with it.
So let's assume that the code I have
here is for a consumer like that.
Now, notice that first thing it's a for
loop, an infinite for loop, right?
It's an infinite for loop,
because that's typical for our consumer,
it's just going to keep receiving,
receiving, receiving.
Now, then in there I select,
the first case
is to receive data on the c channel and
assign it to a, and then I process it.
In this case, I just print a.
And so I'll keep doing that, receiving
data, processing, receiving data, process,
until eventually there's an abort signal.
So somehow an abort happens, and
that can happen any number of ways.
Maybe another Goroutine
receives user input,
the input user types in
something that says quit.
Who knows, right?
So, normally what it wants
to do is that first case,
receive data, process the data.
But at some point there is an abort
that comes in on another channel.
So you have this separate abort channel,
and
if anything comes in on the abort channel,
then you just return.
Right, you just quit the whole process.
Quit the whole loop.
So basically this is normally an infinite
for loop until that abort happens.
So if some data comes in, and
notice that we are not paying attention
to the date of that comes
in on the abort channel.
Notice that it just says case arrow abort.
I didn't say case x equals arrow abort,
I just said case arrow abort.
So I don't care what data is coming into
the abort channel, if something comes
in on the abort channel, that means
the user wants to abort, or somebody is
ordering you to quit this loop, and
then you just return at that point.
So this is a common use of select.
So you can have this separate channel
that happens probably infrequently.
So most of the time, you're going
through the first case, reading data and
processing it off the normal channel,
but every once in a while,
at some point somebody is going to
want to abort your procedure, and so
you have a separate abort
channel that you select from.
Another thing that's done with
select is to have a default case.
So this is a lot like a case switch in c,
it looks like it.
It's not the same, but
it has similar structure.
You can have a default case.
So in this case, we got the regular
cases are waiting on channel 1,
then the second one is
waiting on channel 2.
The default says, look,
I don't want to wait on anything.
If none of those other
cases are satisfied, then
I will execute the default, so I won't
wait, I won't block at all in this case.
When I have a default,
you don't block, you just go and
execute the default if none of
the previous cases are ready.
Thank you.