Point of this first module is to talk about more fully four things.
First thing, is we want to talk about Go,
why it's good, why is unique.
Right? We want to motivate you,
to just tell you why do you need even learn this in
the first place as compared to existing languages because there are many, right?
So, we'll talk about that.
Then, we'll have you start using Go.
So, this specifically means installing
the Go environment and compiling your first program,
you need to get through that before you can go on with the rest of the course.
So, we'll walk you through the installation process and show you how to
compile a program and see if it works as a sanity check for the whole setup.
Then, will start talking about the code organization,
the recommended court organization.
So, workspace, how you define your workspace,
how it should be organized,
how Go code is organized into packages to allow you to share.
So, big point of Go is sharing with other people.
Right? Because if you think about any real software you write, it's always big.
Right? You work with other people's.
Almost never just you alone.
So, you got to share and packages help to make that
easy and to organize the code so you can trade your code with other people.
Then, at the end of this module,
we'll start talking about variables.
Start talk about the language itself,
so the variables, what types there are,
and how do you do scoping,
how variable scoping happens,
how you basically resolve the value of
a variable depending on where it occurs and where it's defined.