So now we're going to start talking a little bit about the Go language,
will broached the topic of variables and talk a little bit about
those variables that are in
every high level language and we'll just see how Go implements it.
A lot of this is very similar to what you've seen in other languages,
some things are a little bit different.
So first there's naming.
Every- you need names.
Names are variables for functions,
you need names to refer to things in your code.
So names for variables and things like that,
they need to start with a letter.
They can have any number of letters and digits and underscores,
they are case sensitive in Go and you can't use keywords.
There's a list of keywords you can google these or look them up but "if", "case",
"package" all the different keywords,
the language you can't use those as the names.
So, variables are basically data stored in memory somewhere.
And every variable has to have a name and a type.
So all variables have to have a declaration,
specifies the name, and the type of the variable.
So, here's a really simple variable declaration.
Just as var, x, int.
So var is the key word for a declaration of a variable.
After that I have the name.
So my name variable is called x and then after that I have the type, var, x, int.
That's it. That's a declaration of this variable x since it's an integer.
And the compiler needs to know what type of variable it is,
what the type is, so it knows how much space to allocate,
what operations to perform that type of thing.
You can declare many on the same line if you want to, just comma-separated.
So var x, y int and you can do that as much as you want.
So variables have types.
Type defines the values that a variable can take
and the operations that can be performed on that variable.
So for instance common types,
basic types, integer, floating point, strings.
Integers, the data, the values that they can take are only integral values right?
They are integers and the operations you can perform are integer arithmetic,
plus, minus, times that sort of
thing and there are a set of other ones we'll talk about them a little more detail.
Floating point, those are the data that they can have,
the values they can have or fractional like
decimal values and there you have a set of operations, arithmetic operations.
Actually they look superficially the same as the integer operations, plus,
times, divide but they may actually be implemented with different hardware right?
Because floating point division say is
significantly more complicated than integer division.
So there's oftentimes as
special hardware just for floating point divide things like this.
We don't have to know that as programmers but
the machine has to know which operation to map it to.
Then strings.
So strings they're a sequence of
bytes represented in unicode and we'll get into that later.
But it's a sequence of bytes,
that's the type of data the values it can take on and
then the operations you can perform on strings. There are many of them.
String comparison, string search,
concatenation, all sorts operations that you can you can perform on a string.
But the point is the type specifies these things.
It specifies what data the variable can hold and how big that data can be right?
Because you need to know
how much space in memory you're going to need to allocate for this.
The compiler needs to know that and also what operations are going to be performed on it.
So what that's for is
eventually the compiler is going to have to take these these operations that you
type and go and compile them into
machine code instructions for whatever the hardware platform is,
and those machine code instructions can be different depending on the type.
So for instance you can easily have an add for an integer,
an integer add up machine code instruction which
is different than a floating point add right?
Integer division which is different than floating point division and so on.
So this is why the compiler needs to know the type so it knows how to do the compilation,
how to convert it into machine code.