[MUSIC]
So we're talking about variables and we're
going to talk about how you initialize
them, but first,
let's finish up the types.
So every variable has to have a type.
And you can make type declarations
where you actually define an alias,
an alternate name for a type.
So sometimes this is useful for
clarity inside a particular application.
For instance here,
it could help you, say you got
you got some kind of application and
it's working on temperatures.
Temperatures are something
that it's manipulating, right?
And every temperature you want
it to be a floating point value,
64 bit floating point value.
So you can define a new type, an alias for
a new type, type Celsius float64.
In that case,
Celsius is exactly the same as float 64.
Now, you can always declare
your variables to be float64,
but Celsius might make sense in
the context of the application, right?
Maybe the application
is about temperatures.
So maybe you want to rename is
[COUGH] just to make it clearer for
you as a programmer.
Also, like the next one, type IDnum int.
Maybe I want to,
maybe I'm making some code that implements
a database of users or something.
And every user has an ID number.
So I know this type,
this concept ID number.
I'd like to, I know it's an integer,
but I want to name it.
I want to give it that name IDnum, so
that I know every variable that it
declares an IDnum, it is an IDnum.
I know something about it just
based on the name of the type.
So once you declare a type like this,
type Celsius float64 or
type IDnum int, you can now declare
variables using that alias.
So I can say var temp Celsius, right?
And now temp is going to be float64
because float64 is aliased by Celsius.
Also, var pid IDnum,
pid is actually an integer.
But we call it an IDnum and
it makes things more clear.
So initializing variable values,
every variable has to be initialized
somehow before you use it.
One way to initialize it is
in the declaration itself.
So you can say var x int = 100.
And that will make x an integer,
it'll declare it as an integer, but
it'll also set it equal 100.
Or you can just say var x = 100.
Now, if you do that you're not
saying you want it as an integer.
So it will infer the type,
it compile with a further type based on
the type of the right hand side value.
So the number 100 is an integer, so
it says x must be an integer,
makes it an integer.
Now, remember,
sometimes this is an issue because maybe
it infers something you don't want, right?
I like to specify myself, but maybe.
So, for instance, say I say x = 100, but
I really want it to be a floating point.
I mean, 100.something, right?
But I call it 100 because that's my
initial temperature that I want, but
I want it to be a floating point value.
This will, if I don't specify, it'll say,
well, 100 could be an integer,
it'll infer it as an integer.
And then if I try to set x to 100.1,
I'll have a problem.
So I like to specify the type,
but you don't have to.
Next up,
initializing after the declaration.
So you can just say var x int, and
then afterwards you could say x = 100.
And then it'll follow the line.
That's another way.
Now, if you don't explicitly initialize
a variable, it'll still get a value.
It'll get the zero value for its type.
So, for instance, say I say var x int.
The 0 value for its type is 0, right?
So x will be automatically assigned
to a 0, initialized to a 0,
if I don't say anything else.
If I say var x string, the zero value for
a string is just the empty string.
So x would be initialized to
the empty string in that case.
Now, another way to initialize variables
is using a short variable declaration.
Now, in this case,
you're performing the declaration and
the initialization together
using the colon equals operator.
So up on the slide x := 100, okay?
When you say that, this is a case where
x has not been declared yet, right?
So this statement actually declares x and
initializes it.
Now, the declaration, what happens is
that when you use that colon equal,
the type that it sets it to be is
whatever's on the right hand side.
So 100 in this case.
It sets, it looks at 100, says, that's an
int and it infers x to be an integer and
then it assigns it to the value 100.
So variable is declared
as a type of expression,
the type that's on the right hand side.
So it does, this type of variable
declaration, it does the declaration and
the assignment together in one
line with this special operator.
You can only do this inside a function.
So you can't do a short variable
declaration outside a function,
that's not legal.
So just know that.